Guide to the M. H. Abrams papers, 1912-2015.
Abrams, M. H. papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
M. H. Abrams papers, 1912-2015.
14-12-4080
Abrams, M. H.(Meyer Howard),
21 cubic feet.
Correspondence, research material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
This collection contains the faculty papers and the correspondence of Professor Mike Abrams. Most documents concern his career at Cornell University.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Meyer Howard "Mike" Abrams was born in Long Branch, New Jersey, on July 23, 1912, in a Jewish-American middle-class family. He went to Harvard where he majored in English literature -- though, interestingly, the Harvard Album for 1934 mentions "law" as his "avocation". Fellow-students included future New York Times foreign affairs columnist Cyrus L. Sulzberger (1913-93) and future historian and Librarian of Congress Daniel J. Boorstin (1914-2004). This is also in Harvard that Abrams met his wife of 71 years, Ruth Claire Gaynes (1917-2008), with whom he would have two children. His first book -- a revised version of his senior's thesis -- was published in 1934 (and reprinted in 1970): "The Milk of Paradise" was about "four eminent English authors [who] were addicted to opium": Coleridge, Crabbe, de Quincey, and Francis Thompson. Young Abrams claimed that "a knowledge of the opium world is essential to complete understanding of their work." After one year at the university of Cambridge as a Henry Fellow, he returned to the United States, but "because there weren't jobs anywhere [during the Great Depression], [he] decided to stay on as a graduate student at Harvard." During World War II he conducted classified research at Harvard's Psycho-Acoustics Laboratory, helping the military solve problems in voice communications by developing highly audible military codes and tests to select personnel with the ability to recognize sounds in a very noisy background. He came to Cornell in 1945 as an assistant professor in the English Department, and was promoted associate professor in 1947 and full professor in 1953. In 1960 he became the first Frederic J. Whiton Professor of English Literature and in 1973 succeeded to the Class of 1916 Professorship until his retirement in 1983. Among his students over the years were literary critics Harold Bloom '51; E.D. Hirsch '50; and novelist Thomas Pynchon '59. Abrams continued to lecture at Cornell and remained a visible and active participant in campus life, giving the keynote lecture at a 2005 James Joyce conference as well as public talks on English poetry in 2008 and 2010, and also attending English department events and Big Red football games. In addition to his service at Cornell, he was a Fulbright Lecturer at the University of Malta (1953), a Fellow at the Center for Advanced Studies in Behavioural Sciences at Stanford (1967-88), a Visiting Fellow at all Souls College, Oxford University (1977), a member of the Founders' Group of the National Humanities Center, and was named Chairman of the Council of Scholars of the Library of Congress in 1984. "The Mirror and the Lamp: Romantic Theory and the Critical Tradition" (1953) was cited in 1957 in a poll of 250 literary critics and scholars as one of the "five works published the last thirty years which... have contributed the most to an understanding of literature." Also in the late 1950s, Abrams was approached by the W.W. Norton Company about compiling "a definitive anthology of English literature". The resulting book sold millions of copies, and remains an enduring reference for high school and college students. Abrams was general editor of the "Norton Anthology" through seven editions from 1962 to 2000. His other books include “Natural Supernaturalism: Tradition and Revolution in Romantic Literature” (1971); "The Glossary of Literary Terms," first published in 1957; and "Wordsworth: A Collection of Critical Essays" (1972). In 2014, President Barack Obama awarded him the National Humanities Medal "for broadening the study of literature." Mike Abrams died in Ithaca on April 21, 2015.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
This collection contains the faculty papers and the correspondence of Professor Mike Abrams. Most documents concern his career at Cornell University. Also a oral history interview conducted on February 18, 2008 by Jonathan Culler and Neil Hertz.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Abrams, M. H. 1912-2015.; Cornell University. English Department.; Cornell University. English Department
Subjects:
English literature -- Study and teaching.; English literature -- Study and teaching
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Class Materials
Box
Subseries I a. General Course Material
Subseries I b. Honors Seminars
Subseries I c. Various English Classes
Subseries I d. Harvard English 140b: Literary Criticism in the 18th century
Subseries I e. English 90/411: Psychology of Literature
Subseries I f. English 202: English Literary Tradition
Subseries I g. English 251
Subseries I h. English 252
Subseries I i. English 313: 18th century Literature
Subseries I j. English 314: 18th Century Poetry and Prose
Subseries I k. English 417/418/438: Masterworks of the Romantic Period
Series II. Lectures
Subseries II a. Outside Lecture Correspondence and Invitations
Series III. Correspondence
Series IV. Publications
Subseries IV a. The Mirror and the Lamp
Subseries IV b. Natural Supernaturalism
Subseries IV c. How to Do Things With Texts/Doing Things With Texts
Subseries IV d. The Fourth Dimension of a Poem and Other Essays
Subseries IV e. Essays
Subseries IV f. Book Reviews
Series V. W.W. Norton Materials
Series VI. Harvard Psycho-Acoustic Laboratory
Series VII. Reprints
Series VIII. Personal
Series IX. Miscellaneous
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Class Materials
  - Subseries I a. General Course Material
    - English Tutorial Board, undated (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - English Tutorial Board bibliography, 1940-1942 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Suggested Thesis Subjects, undated (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Discussion Group: Problems in Language, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Grad student directories, 1967-1980 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Written PhD examinations, 1960-1982 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Mimeograph stencils, undated (Box 17, Folder 27)
  - Subseries I b. Honors Seminars
    - English 403: Approaches to Literature, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - English 403: Approaches to Literature reading notes, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - English 403: Approaches to Literature, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - English 404: Approaches to Poetry, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - English 390: Convention and Individual Talent, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - English 390: Approaches to Poetry meetings of the course, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - English 390: The Criticism of Lyric Poetry, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - English 492: Approaches to Literature, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - English 492: Seminar in Poetry, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - English 494: Honors Seminar Poetry, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - English 494: The Criticism of Poetry, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - English 494: The Criticism of Poetry, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - English 492.6: Approaches to Poetry, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - English 491.G: The Criticism of Poetry, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - English 491.G: The Criticism of Poetry, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Subseries I c. Various English Classes
    - English 402: Grades, meeting notes, seating charts, course information, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Graduate Seminars: various possibilities, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - English 675: Romantic Poetry, Romantic Criticism, Biographia Literaria, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - English 675: Romantic Poetry, Romantic Criticism, Biographia Literaria, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - English 553: Studies in English Poetry, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - English 554: Studies in English Poetry, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - English 500: Critical and Scholarly Perspectives, The Prelude, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Society of the Humanities "Interpretation and Understanding in the Criticism of Literature", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Philosophy 593: Seminar in Philosophy and Literary Criticism, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - English 697: Literary Theory and Literary Criticism, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - English 697: Literary Theory and Literary Criticism xeroxed materials, students xeroxes, etc., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - English 500B: Critical and Scholarly Perspectives, Biographia Literaria, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - English 699: Critical and Scholarly Perspectives, Keats, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - English 771: The Interpretation of Poetry, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - English 771: The Interpretation of Poetry topics, reading notes, xeroxed essays, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Xerox: Literary Interpretation and the Subjective Correlative", undated (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - English 702: Ancients and the Moderns, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - English 641: Modern Theory of Literature and Art, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - English 642: Wordsworth's Prelude, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - English 642: Reading notes and xeroxed essays, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - English 642: Romantic Poems, and a novel, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - English 740: English Masterworks, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - English 642: Romantic Masterworks, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Correspondence with Stephen Greenblatt, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - English 403: Approaches to Literature, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Graduate Seminar: Wordsworth and Coleridge, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Graduate Seminar: Wordsworth and Coleridge, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - English 515: Coleridge's "Dejection" and its background. Course notes., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - English 515: Romantic Poetic forms- "Dejection", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - English 515: Studies in the Romantic Lyric. Notes on the seminar., 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - English 515: Romantic Poetic forms- "Dejection", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - English 515: Coleridges, Biographia Literaria, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Graduate seminar: Structure and Symbol in Major Romantic Poems, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - English 631: Structure and Symbol in Major Romantic Poems, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - English 543: Studies in English Poetry, reading notes, etc., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - English 543: Studies in English Poetry, general, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - English 543: Studies in English Poetry, course meetings, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - English 543: Studies in English Poetry, course meetings, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - English 631: The Romantic Period, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - English 640: Studies in English Poetry, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - English 517: Idea and Design in Longer Romantic Poems, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - English 517: Structure and Imagery in Romantic Poems, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - English 517: Structure and Imagery in Romantic Poems, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - English 572: Structure and Imagery in Romantic Poems, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - English S-150c: Romantic Poetry outline of lectures and lecture notes (Harvard), 1954 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - English S-150c: Romantic Poetry, summer school, theory, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Literary criticism courses material, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - English 35a: Bible and Shakespeare Questions, 1940-1941 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - English 111: Freshman miscellaneous, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - The Eighteenth Century Achievement in Didactic Poetry, 1952 (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - Subseries I d. Harvard English 140b: Literary Criticism in the 18th century
    - State of Scholarshiop in 18th century criticism, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - 18th century literary criticism, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Detailed outline of lectures, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - I. Introduction, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - II. The Nature of Poetry: Imitation vs. Expression, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - III. Poetry as Imitation, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - IV. Poetry as Expression, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - V. The Function of Poetry, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - VI. The Criterion of Truth to Nature, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - VII. The Criterion of Truth, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - VIIIa. Poetry as Self Revelation, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - VIIIb. Criticism of Truth, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - IX. The Psychology of Composition, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - X. The War of the Faculties, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - XI. Poetic Inspiration, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - XII. Genius, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - XIII. Conclusion: Psych of Composition, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - XIV. The Theory of Criticism: The Rules of Poetry, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - XV. The Special Rules, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - XVI. Sanctions of the Rules, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - XVII. Sanctions for the Rules, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - XVIII. The Standard of Taste, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - XIX. The Drift Toward Relativism, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - XX. The Methods of Applied Criticism, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - XXI. The Language of Poetry, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - XXII. The Language of Poetry, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - XXIII. Main Changes in Taste in the 18th century, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - XXIV: An Analysis of Temple's Essay, "Of Poetry", circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Subseries I e. English 90/411: Psychology of Literature
    - Harvard Psych. Lit. Reserved Books, Outline of Lectures, Reading Lists, Exams, 1940-1948 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Exams, Thesis Subjects, Assigned Reading, Outlines, 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - The Psychology of Language, "I Remember" exercise, 1940s (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Harvard: Protocols on "Vertue", 1940 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Reading lists, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Introduction, 1941, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - I-XI. Language, 1945, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - XII. Language, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Analysis of a Poem, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - X. Humor, 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - XI. Psychology of Composition, undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - XII. Relation of a Literary Work and Other Works, undated, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - XIII. The Interpretation of Poetry, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Humor (old lecture), 1945 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - XVII. Background to Present Day Psych. Of Lit., 1945 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - XVIII. Historical background, Literature as Expression, 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - XIX. Artist in his Work, 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - History of Psych. Of Comp., 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - XXV-XXVIII. Determination by Former Works, 1940, 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Subseries I f. English 202: English Literary Tradition
    - Course information, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Course information, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Course information, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Course information, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Course information, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Course information, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - English Materials, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - English Literary Tradition, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Course information, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Course information, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Course information, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Course information, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - The English Literary Tradition: planning, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - From: Edmund Wilson, The Triple Thinkers, Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Seminar: Henry James, The Turn of the Screw, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - From: Edmund Wilson, The Triple Thinkers, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Seminar: Austen, Pride and Prejudice, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Meter, Stanza-forms, etc., 1980 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Meter, Stanza-forms, etc., 1981 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - James, The Ambassadors, 1978-1979, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Make-up Exams, 1975-1990 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - I. Introduction: Neoclassicism, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - II-III. John Dryden, 1982, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
    - IV. John Bunyan, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - V. Alexander Pope, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - VI. Alexander Pope, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - VII. Alexander Pope, Lady Mary Montague, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - VIII. Jonathan Swift, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - IX. Jonathan Swift, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Johnson, "The Vanity of Human Wishes", undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Johnson, Rasselas, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Thomas Gray, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - William Blake, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - William Blake, The Marriage of Heaven and Hell, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - I. Wordsworth, 1987, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - II. Wordsworth, undated, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - III. Wordsworth, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Wordsworth (4), undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - IV. Coleridge Ancient Mariner, 1978, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - V. Coleridge Ancient Mariner (English 252), 1951 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - VI. Coleridge: the "Conversation Poems", 1951 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - V. Coleridge, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - VI. Byron: Lyrics and Childe Harold, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - VII. Byron: Don Juan, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - VIII. Shelley, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - IX. Shelley: Life and Death, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - X. Keats: 2 poems of the far away and long ago, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - XI. Keats: The Odes, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - XII. Carlyle, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - XIII. Xarlyle: Past and Present, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - XIV. Tennyson, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - XV. Tennyson: In Memoriam, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - XVI. Browning: The Poetic Innovator, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - XVII. Browning: The Dramatic Monologue, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - XVIII. Arnold, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - XIX. Yeats, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Subseries I g. English 251
    - Schedules, syllabi, exams, 1949-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Assignments and exams (Norton Anthology), 1966-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Section meetings, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Discussion groups, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Recorders and voice- Elizabethan performance, 1959-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - I. Introduction to English literature, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - II. Epic and Romance, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - III. Chaucer (1), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - IV. Chaucer (2), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - V. Chaucer (3), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - VI. The Popular Ballad, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - VII. The Renaissance in England, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - VIII. The Elizabethan Lyric, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - IX. Spenser (1), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - X. Spenser's Faerie Queen, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - XI. Marlowe's Dr. Faustus, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - XII-XIII. Henry IV (1), 1963, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - XIV. The XVII Century (outline), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - XV. Jonson and the Cavalier Lyric, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - XVI. John Donne, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - XVII. Donne and the Metaphysical Tradition, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - XVIII. Milton's Paradise Lost (1), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - XIX. Milton's Paradise Lost (2), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - XX. Restoration Comedy: "The Way of the World", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - XXI. Neo-Classicism and Pope, essay on criticism, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - XXII. John Dryden, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - XXIII. Pope's Essay on Man, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - XXIV. Pope: The Rape of the Lock, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - XXV. Jonathan Swift, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - XXVI. Samuel Johnson, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - XXVII. William Blake, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - (251 and 252)Passages for Identification on Exams, 1953, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Subseries I h. English 252
    - Exams, outlines, syllabi, miscellany, 1940-1963 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - General (Norton Anthology), 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Section meetings, 1951, 1959, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Saturday meetings (Norton Anthology), 1954, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - I. The Romantic Period, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - II. Wordsworth: The Development of a Poet, 1951, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - III. Wordsworth: Tintern Abbey, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - IV. Wordsworth: Poem of Solitude, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Coleridge's "Dejection: An Ode", 1951, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - VII. Byron: Childe Harold, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - VIII. Byron: Don Juan, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - IX. Shelley: Poet of Ideas, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - X. Shelley: The Lyric Poet, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - XI. Shelley: The Triumph Over Death, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Keats: Strangeness in Beauty, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Keats: The Ode, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Carlyle, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Tennyson, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Tennyson: In Memoriam, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - II. Browning as Poetic Innovator, Undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Arnold, Undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Aestheticism and Decadence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - G.B. Shaw, Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - G.B. Shaw: St. Joan, Undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - G.M. Hopkins, 1955-1965 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - W.B. Yeats, Undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Subseries I i. English 313: 18th century Literature
    - Junior course miscellaneous, 1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Summer session miscellaneous, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Addison- Original The Spectator paper, 1711 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Lecture II. Some Neoclassic Beliefs and Values, 1953, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - III. Neoclassic Criticism, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - IV. The Art of the Heroic Couplet, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - V-VII. Literature and Society in the 18th Century, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - VIII. Basic Themes in 18th Century Thought: Deism, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - X. The Great Chain of Being and 18th "optimism", 1953 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - XI-XII. Sympathy, Sensibility, and Sentiment2, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - XIII-XIV. The Art of Satire in 18th century: The Rape of the Lock, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - XIV-XVII. Pope's Haratio Satires: Examples and Techniques, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - XVIII-XX. Jonathan Swift, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - XXI. Johnson the Poet, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - XXII. Johnson's Rasselas, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - XXIII. Rasselas and Candide, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - XXIV. Boswell and Biography, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - XXV-XXVI. The Poetic Revolution of the Mid Century: Primitivism and the Return to Nature, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - XXVII. Collins: Allegoric and Descriptive Odes, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - XXVIII-XXIX. Gray's Odes and Elegy, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - XXX. Descriptive Poetry in the Early 18th Centruy (Pope and Dyer), 1953 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - XXXI-XXXII. Wordsworth and Thomson's Seasons, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - XXXIII. Realism and Ruralism: Goldsmith and Crabbe, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - XXXIV. William Cowper, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - XXXV. The Lyric in the 18th century, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - XXXVI-XXXXVIII. Robert Burns, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - XXXVIII. Werther and Wertherism, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - XXXIX-XLI. William Blake, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Examinations, 1953-1960 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - English Honors Examinations, 1953-1967 (Box 2, Folder 65)